Well, make your public hearing pretty easy, George, if nobody shows up. Yes. Well, we have a quorum of commissioners,
>> but we have no public. So,
I'm still going to call to order
the
public hearing
scheduled for Monday, 04/04/2022
at 7PM to hear testimony and comments on the following
proposed changes to the Andover Inland Wetlands and Water Courses Commission regulations.
Present for the Commission
myself,
Chairman Elliott,
Commissioner Jed Larson,
and Commissioner William Monroe.
Also present: Agent Wagner
and Board Clerk Abby Winter.
Seeing no members of the public
in
any form of this grid
or waiting
in the waiting room or otherwise
showing any intention of attending
this hearing.
I believe we can wait a couple of beats
and then call for an adjournment.
Jed, we need some of the crowd from the Planning and Zoning hearings is what we need here.
They seem to be a lot more popular.
I bet you get a whole lot of folks coming out about the hearing on
regulations
on
certain sorts of businesses
that might
be proposed
for our quiet little town.
>> I do
think we will have some interest there. Yep, there's a couple interesting things going on right now. Yep,
>> sure enough.
Okay, so I'll move to adjourn the meeting.
I get a second on that. I'll second it. Okay,
so motion seconded.
Commissioner Larson.
Aye.
Commissioner Munro?
And I also vote aye, so the motion to adjourn carries
unanimously.
I'll now call to order our regular meeting
The same participants.
Anybody got any
changes
to the agenda?
Okay,
then next up we've got the minutes
from 03/07/2022,
regular meeting. Those were posted
and distributed
some time back,
and hope you all have had a chance to review them.
>> I'll make a motion that we approve the minutes from March 7.
>> I'll second it. Okay, so motion and second to approve.
Any further discussion?
Seeing none, we'll get a vote on the motion. Commissioner Larson?
Aye.
Commissioner Munro?
Aye. And I also vote aye, so the motion carries unanimously.
Well, again, no public, so no public comment.
And our new business consists,
first of all,
adopting
or approving, as the case may be, the draft regulations.
The revisions,
just
to make sure that we're all on the same page here,
and
because I've got a ton of revisions floating around on my hard drive,
the
version that I refer to
is the one that's currently posted on the website.
It's titled,
full title is IWWRegulationsproposed
revisednine.
Nine. 2021
layoutrevisedrevisedseventeen.
2022.
PDF.
>> I'm not sure if that's the one I was reading.
>> That's why I spelled it out, Bill, because I know that, as they say, there's so there have been so many
versions floating around,
but this one, you know, it incorporates all of our actual revisions.
And then
I believe it was Agent Wagner's
hand in reformatting
the document to
make it look better
and get all the headings lined up and whatnot.
>> Yeah. I just
draft on the title and then the date so we knew which one it was. And then Right. Some of those page numbers were messed up, so I went and fixed those. And then,
yeah, it was just it was just
visual stuff.
>> Yeah, well this, you know, this document started out as a,
I don't know, the
old PDF which was scanned from our previous regulations,
and
lord knows it took a
whole lot of effort, mainly while I principally,
to
get those
get that scanned document
into something that could be edited in Word
and
combing out all of the errors and replacing all the DEPs with DEEPs
and so forth and so on.
But I trust that after all those all that effort and all those revisions, we've got something that we can post
without fear
or trepidation.
So I will move that we adopt
those revised regulations.
Effective
I'm sure I can't remember there's some time period involved. We still have to notify
DEEP
about
the hearing and the
adoption of the regulations,
but essentially
to be
posted and promulgated as soon as possible.
I'll second. Thank you, Commissioner Larson.
So, is there any further discussion
regarding the adoption of the regulations?
>> I do have a question. Like I said, I think I I
was reading the
Andover Inland Wetlands and Water Courses Regulation
effective 07/01/2008.
So that's not the right one.
>> That well, that is what we are currently operating under.
The proposed revisions
were
again posted as such
under
that section.
I don't have my web browser open at the moment,
and I'm having a little problem with internet connection
on my
desktop
computer.
Abi, can you pull that up?
I'm trying to do it, but it's not working.
>> So I have these here. I'm guessing you're looking at the
top one here, proposed revised.
Unless you're looking at the summary proposed changes to the regulations.
>> Right, well, what we are adopting will be in fact the the top line.
Okay, the IWA regulations proposed revised
layout revised,
and that's what we're going to, you know, that's what we need to adopt.
The summary of changes briefly,
I mean,
the summary of summary of changes is basically
revising it to update
in accordance with state statutes.
There's
one additional as of right activity:
dry
hydrants,
such as used by fire departments or the emergency,
water withdrawal,
or
I guess the installation of a dry hydrant is now in activity permitted as of right.
There is some new language
regarding
situations where there
conservation or preservation
easements or other
encumbrances on
sites that might be
looking for
a permit for wetlands activities.
There's new requirements
for
notification of adjoining municipalities
and
regulations
dealing with
essentially
conditions
regarding what time of year
an activity can be carried out. So, for example, if we were
permitting an activity that might have
an impact on,
just for example,
some kind of amphibians,
that we would be able to restrict that activity so that it wouldn't occur
during times of
amphibian breeding activity.
And
finally,
there are new terms for expiration of permits.
Again, these are all changes that are required
by
legislative action, new state statutes,
revisions of state statutes, and so forth. I
>> see.
Okay.
I I
I was reading about
the the the I thought was interesting was the current inventory of the regulated areas, like in Andover,
you know, like like
Andover
Lake and
Pop River.
And I
was wondering why the two streams that are feeding the lake aren't aren't
part of the regulated areas.
Scugbrook and Cheneybrook?
>> Right. Well, of course, those are also
those are subject to
the 100 foot
Upland Review area.
And I don't know why they were not deemed to be of
additional concern
when the regulations were first
developed.
And
again, there's been no proposal to change them
that would
affect
our decision with
the revisions
tonight.
Know, the document that you're looking at is what was
submitted to DEEP
and
was the subject of
the hearing,
so we can't make any alterations
at It this
>> does say
Cheney Brook is one of the areas.
Oh,
so it
should be it's it's G under there. So Cheney Brook and it's got Andover Lake Brook in parentheses.
>> Oh, okay. Oh, Andover Lake Brook. Yeah. That's considered Cheney Brook, I guess. Right.
Okay.
The other thing I thought you guys were going to be talking about the whole thing with the bond
bonding and insurance do we actually do that we do we
we have that kind of
do we do that? I don't, I haven't seen that since I've been on the Commission.
>> Nor have I since I came on the Commission.
I
don't know quite what kinds of circumstances
would call for it,
but certainly we haven't seen any occasions
where it seemed warranted.
However, the regulations,
you know, authorize us to do so,
and again, that's
a statutory
authority.
>> I think that planning
and zoning over in the gravel pit area, we put a bond on the
property owner there just to ensure that there was money available at the end
to properly restore
that if
for some reason the property owner just left and
let it in a condition that wasn't
what we were
spelling out in
the restoration plan. So we've got a little money set aside so that if they don't restore it,
we can go in and get that job done and have it restored
to the manner that we were looking for.
>> And be sure that it gets paid for.
Okay,
we had also discussed the application and permit fees.
Those seem to be in line with what other
agencies are
charging and
seem to be adequate
to cover our consulting fees and so forth. So,
there
didn't seem to be any need to change
that section.
And other than that,
they say the brief summary I gave you
amounted to all that we were required to change.
Okay,
thank you.
>> Any
further
questions or comments?
If not, we'll proceed
to a vote on the motion to approve.
Commissioner Larson?
Aye.
>> Commissioner Monroe?
And I vote aye. So the motion carries unanimously.
We
will move ahead,
Adrienne Wagner and I, to
get these submitted,
you know, to notifymake
proper notification to DEEP
and
to move the process forward in terms of getting these
legally posted. They have to be deposited
with the town clerk, etc.
So, we'll make sure that those I's
get crossed and those T's get dotted, and we can move on now to the other item of new business.
The
adoption
and approval of a revised set of standard permit conditions.
Now previously,
in the regulations currently
posted under 2008,
the
quote standard conditions
are included as an appendix
to the regulations
along
with other appendices that
have some other legal
advice.
But
Agent Wagner
contacted
Attorney Brantz
regarding
the inclusion of standard conditions in the regulations,
and we were advised that while we could do it, and
he had some
pros,
you know, someone
particular reason
for including it,
but it's not required.
And it seemed to me that we would have greater flexibility
in dealing
with
what amounts to administrative
procedures
to keep them, you know, as a separate body
rather than including them in the regulations per set.
The key is that
if we have
standard conditions
that they be included
in any sets of plans and that they be included
in the permit
approval
so that they don't fall between the cracks.
But
on the other hand,
if we don't do that, and even if they're in the regulations,
then they can still fall between the cracks, because
it's been pointed out that contractors
working on landscapers
working
on-site
are
unlikely
to have a
copy of the regulations and standard conditions
readily at hand.
So, if we put them on the plans,
then we know that they're there and that, you know, whoever's working off that page
should be aware
of those conditions.
Another, I think, noteworthy improvement
in the
standard conditions was that
under current condition number seven
regarding soil erosion materials,
the previous
standard conditions called for a certified engineer, a PE,
to be responsible for planning and siting. That seemed to be
excessive for the types of situations we often deal with,
for example, the placement of
silt fence to prevent sand from getting into
Andover Lake
from that project that we just approved.
So,
anybody should be able to follow best management practices
there
without necessarily having engineering
certification.
So, I thought that was a distinct improvement.
Otherwise,
I'll leave it open for comment on,
the
standard conditions. If anybody has anything
that they should think should be included or modification
of language,
now is the time to bring it up.
Agent Wenger, I believe you said that the
Todd Wyndham
also has.
Do they have standard conditions for the board that you're on or Commissioner? No, not that I've ever ever seen. We just add conditions
>> as necessary,
you know. Mhmm. We don't have, like, a set of standard ones that are
>> k. Some of these things are,
for example, number four is,
it's a statutory requirement.
These are not unique
to,
you know, our regulations.
I think it is a good idea to have
a set that you can refer to as sort of boilerplate,
and it doesn't
preclude us
from adding special conditions or, you know, particular conditions
to
an application approval
as needed.
>> I agree. I think it's a great idea. I like it.
>> Sort of a shorthand,
and
again, it
seems to have
worked
previously
in the sense that we haven't gotten any complaints,
and we haven't had any issues
by simply referring to standard conditions
when we approve permits.
Okay,
well,
if there are no
further
comments or suggestions,
I would entertain a motion to
approve and adopt
the,
again,
revised standard conditions
full title IWWC
underscore standard underscore permit underscore conditions underscore draft
underscore
nine
period 29
period
two zero two one.
>> Document I make a motion to approve and adopt the revised standard permit conditions
that Chairman Elliott
just
enunciated.
I'll second that.
>> Okay,
and if no further discussion, I'll call for a vote on the motion. Commissioner Larson.
Aye
Commissioner Monroe.
Aye,
and I also vote aye, so the motion carries unanimously.
We can change the title now from draft to adopted
and post that. I think they're
putting it in with the regulations as a under the
you could say that it's an advisory
document, you know, it's not part of our regulations,
but it's something we want
applicants to be aware of.
>> Yeah, I can put in, set up the website so that it's, you know, it's like right with
the current regulations.
>> Yeah, that should be good.
Okay,
next item of business,
commission vacancies.
Well, we posted I contacted
Amanda Gibson.
She posted
my
little plea
for volunteers.
The
response has been
nil,
and frankly I'm at a loss
to see what we can do to recruit.
I'm jealous, Jed, because I saw that PNZ has a full complement of members and alternates.
>> Well, and my recommendation
to you would be I would reach out to Gary McCullough,
who is now Yeah, right, the new guy in town. New guy in town who is very familiar with what the Inland West Coast. And
he worked for me on the planning and zoning one time. There was
a guy and
he was not in favor of a
subdivision we were doing. And
he asked lots of good questions. And I know we didn't
act the way he was hoping to.
But after we were done, I emailed him and said,
you know, you probably weren't happy with the outcome, but you certainly have a good knowledge of it. And I
like your thought process. Would you have any interest being on the Commission?
Right. Okay.
>> You want to put your oar in for real? Here's your opportunity.
>> Exactly.
And so,
know, Gary's neutered down. I don't know if he's retired yet or not or how much he's working, but might just
be something right up his alley.
>> That's a notion. I will.
I believe we have some
contact
information for him,
think I'll reach out to him. I'll make a note of that. But yeah, I think, you know, obviously personal connections are
very meaningful in this situation.
Unfortunately, I've drawn a blank on
that.
Some logical
choices
demurred or otherwise
active in
other
areas, other commissions or agencies.
As it's been pointed out, you know, it's a small town and we have just as many boards and commissions
as anybody else,
and
we have a lot of people already
who are
double dipping. Either you don't like being on Board of Selectmen and
Board of Ed or Board of Selectmen and Board of Finance.
There's Jed, who's the Chairman of P and Z, and on
Inland Wetlands,
ex officio, I guess, but
there's only so much
we can ask
of the people who are most active
in keeping things running in the town.
Butso anyhow, if you have any further ideas, just let me know if you have any personal contacts that you think
could be
induced.
>> I do have a question. Sure, Bill. Chairman George.
Do they have to be a resident of Andover? Yes, you have to be technically
>> an elector
of the town. According to the that's in the Charter. It is true for all of our Commission boards and commissions. You have to be an elector
of the town. Now,
I think that in the broader sense that an elector doesn't necessarily live in town. If you have property
in town,
you may be regarded as an elector.
I'm not sure if that applies to memberships,
because obviously
it applies to voting on the budget.
Yeah,
>> I think everybody that's on the Commission needs to be registered to vote in town.
>> Right, yeah, that's the key, register to vote in town.
I mean, it's very efficient getting business done with three people, but that means that, you know, we have a bare quorum
to
make a meeting. If one of us
is missing, well, there's no meeting.
>> Well, heaven forbid, what if I wanted to put in
an application?
>> Exactly,
and that it would
affect the clock.
It's
true. We haven't had much in the way of application activity, one so far this year.
Yeah, it's been been quiet. Maybe lumber prices are.
Discouraging
construction.
Yeah.
>> I did reach out to was that Kate Casey Shay.
I think it was 436 Lake Road, that new house that you had approved.
I remember talking to him about
asking if he was interested in joining the commission, and he seemed like he might be, but he hasn't they I don't think they're living. Pretty sure they're not living there now. So Oh, okay. I'm moving. He's not officially a resident yet.
Okay.
>> But it's a good point, Joe. Keep keep in mind as soon as he is living there. You know Yeah.
We'll reach
out to him because we treated the guy pretty good, you know, and you've had a lot of interactions with him. Yeah. He did he did pause and seemed like he was thinking about it. So,
>> yeah, I'll definitely when I when I know they're they're all moved in, I'll probably try and reach out again or George. I
>> got the
we should ask
our our registrars of voters for a heads up when we have new
voters
enrolling.
They send them a pamphlet. Right, they
>> would be the first to know.
Right, yeah, as part of your voter registration package,
here's an invitation
to serve
on the town commission.
Okay,
well,
okay, so actually I will reach out to Gary McCullough and
see if he has any thoughts on that.
Okay,
moving on.
Agent Wagner, anything to report from your
office?
Nothing.
>> Nothing too crazy. There was a
Gary McCullough called. They they finished the wall.
They constructed that perched beach.
Mhmm.
>> Posted
pictures on under his application.
If you wanted to feel Yeah.
Came out pretty good. They changed the design slightly. He had called me and they
used
Belgian block instead of pressure treated lumber around the Perch Beach, but it was the same same size, same elevation,
everything.
>> Again, price is right thing.
Blocks may have just been a good move
financially as well.
>> Yeah,
yeah, and then,
so yeah, so that's all done. He's just waiting to get a
get some topsoil and put it over the old
sandy area and plant some seed and stuff, that's that one's pretty much finished up now.
They completed the wall pretty quickly.
And then the other thing is that permit link online permitting.
I remember talking
to you guys about that a while ago. That's
finally
available to use.
So it's the same application that I ran by you guys.
That's on there. Everything's online now. I'm trying to figure out how best to
My thought was to keep posting everything,
all the materials
on the website
because they'll be posted. They'll be uploaded to permit link, but I think it's easier for
everybody to find them on the, you know, on the current form.
>> I think that that's a convenient form. Having things
in a,
you know, there's a,
as it were,
section where we can look for new permits.
Each permit has all the materials
posted there.
It may be a little bit redundant,
but again, I think you're right that it is convenient
>> Yeah. To have it accessible like that. That's what I was thinking. So I was thinking of kind of keeping that up and kind of trying to
slowly work in. Like I have
paper copies that
are exact
replicas of the online one that people could use if they don't have access to a, you know, computer scanner or something. So I was trying to, you know, instead of just going straight to the online, you have to use this computer, you know, maybe try and do like a hybrid form.
>> Mhmm. People that are We we we we still have to make provision for
paper.
>> Yeah.
That's my thought, so that'll that'll be kind of ongoing, but that's more on on my end. Right. But I think everything's gonna pretty much look the same on your end. So Yeah. If you have you know, if you if you if, as you say, you have a form
>> that gives you the same information, the same order and everything, then
obviously that can be scanned and uploaded,
and we can look at it the same as we would be looking at the output
from filling out a form
online.
We'll get the same information.
Yeah. Okay,
good. Well, that's good to hear. I'll click
over that way next time I'm
on the IWWC
main page.
Did I have two questions, George?
Go right ahead.
>> So
when
Gary puts his topsoil down
over the sandy area,
I'm hoping that he's going back to put some
erosion and sediment control in on that too because that
is all just going to wash down into the lake most likely otherwise, unless you've got
something special there.
I can't remember if that was in the procedure that we were talking about or respiration or not,
but
you looked like you just had a nice sandy beach area. I guess I'm surprised to hear that he was gonna put topsoil on it to to
grow grass in that. Looked to me like he got exactly what he was looking for with beach.
In a matter of speaking.
>> Yeah, I think he was like lightly. I don't think he was planning on like tearing it up and and removing
it. I think it was more of the the stuff up
above the wall that he wanted to put the seed in.
Oh Okay,
>> Around that buffer area. Not over where the sandy beach is on there. I
guess the other question I had, George, is if
we could get hard copies of the new
regulations
once
they're
in effect
that
Good point. I could save a couple sheets of paper and not have to run it off on my own printer here.
>> Yeah, I could take care of that if you want. Okay.
>> Yeah, that'd be great.
Yeah.
You can pass them out at our next real meeting.
>> Positivity rates headed back up.
We're
in the border today.
>> We've got
a new variant.
Yep. Coming right down the pike.
So just when you thought it was safe to go on the water.
Alrighty,
okay,
so is that it for
>> agent report and enforcement actions? Yes, that's all I got.
>> Well, then
final, well, the next item on the agenda, recall that our next regular meeting
Monday,
05/02/2022
at 7PM,
assuming we have any business to take care of
at that time.
We'll
keep you posted,
if any applications show up in the interim.
With that,
we can entertain a motion for adjournment.
I move we adjourn.
Second it.
>> Okay, and that's nondebatable,
so proceed directly to a vote. Commissioner
Larson.
Aye.
Commissioner Monroe.
And I also vote aye. So the motion to adjourn
at
07:38PM
carries unanimously.
Abby, thanks for being here,
and we look forward to seeing you in a minute soon.
With that, I guess we can all press the little red leave button and say good night.
Thanks everybody. Be
in touch.